北平城发生“虎烈拉”瘟疫
Cholera epidemic is raging in Peking.
因疫情严重，从即日起北平城戒严
The city is under strict quarantine to prevent further infections.
军部要求尽快将研究成果
Army requests research results as quickly as possible
应用于华北战区
for use on Northeastern front.
细菌专家已秘密前往你处.绝密.
Germ warfare experts are travelling in disguise to your location. Top-secret!
一九四二年末，虎烈拉瘟疫突发于北平
Near the end of 1942, a cholera epidemic raged in Peking,
百姓大量死亡
killing many of the city's inhabitants.
据当时人们传说，有四位江湖大盗
People who remember tell of four bandits
以奇法抢得解药，并救民于水火
who stole the cure from the Japanese and saved the city.
后来老人们回忆
The old say they were real,
确曾有人见过这四位大侠
and some people remember seeing them.
人们说他们是疯子
They were described as INSANE.
但也有人说他们是英雄！
But others said they were HEROES!
打劫！
This is a stick-up!
不许动，不然打死你！
Nobody moves, or I'll make you dead!
枪响了！
BANG!
哪儿跑？
Where did he go?
快点快点  跟上  说你呢快
Move! After him! You, hurry up!
跑哪儿去了
Where did he go?
我上那边去看
I'll go look over there!
干什么呢  跟紧的
Hey, hurry up!
跟上
Go find him!
后头干么呢
Why are you lagging!
快点跟上  说你呢快  跑步
Get moving, after him! Yeah, you! Run!
日本人
Japanese?
支那人啊
Shinajin.
我去
Oh my!
支你娘的个腚你支
Shinajin my backside!
（别动）
(Hold it now!)
（欢迎光临）
(Welcome!)
老婆呀
Honeybun,
不要欢迎了
don't welcome him.
强  强盗来了
He's... he's a robber!
老婆  把枪给他
Honeybun, give his gun...
给  给  给
give... give... give...
给给  给它撅了
give it... give it the bend!
别动
Don't move!
谁动
Anybody moves,
谁动  我给谁爆出个眼来
and I'll dig out your eyeball!
嗯什么嗯  你在拉屎啊
Ungh ungh ungh you pinchin' one off?
老婆  枪哩
Honeybun, the gun!
傻鳖你
Son of a pooch!
起来
Get up!
老婆
Honeybun,
去  给他们松绑
go untie them!
然后咱们去报官
Then we'll report this scoundrel!
别别别
Don't don't don't!
你接着牛逼呀
You're a big man now!
别别别别
Don't don't don't!
轻点
Not so hard!
混蛋
Craven fool!
快把我们放了
Let us go!
不然把你们全部处死
Or you all die slowly and painfully!
快放人  混蛋
Let us go! Craven fools!
完了完了完了
Oh me oh my oh no!
屎拉自己裤裆来了
I just pinched one off in my pants!
是鬼子你不说
They're Japanese!
嘛呢
What in the name of...
谁呀
Who is this?
不知道哪里跑出来的二流子
A scoundrel from the saints know where.
你他娘才是二流子呢
You're the turtlin' scoundrel!
这二位谁呀
And who are they?
这二位
These two
是那个二流子啊
are Japanese officers
抓来的日本太君哪
that scoundrel kidnapped!
别动
Stay your hand!
戏子呀
Actor!
我每个月四十斤白面养着你
I spend 40 pounds of flour a month to feed you!
你都忘了吗
I'm in charge here!
捆日本人
Kidnapping the Japanese!
那是什么罪你知道的
You know how serious a crime this is!
我本是卧龙岗散淡的人
My talents have slept too long in disguise...
戏子呀
Actor!
让我们聊聊正事吧
This here is serious business!
这小子敢劫太君
So this fellow kidnaps Japanese?
八成是八
80% he's an 8!
八路
8th Route?!
八路可就更不好惹了
The 8th Route Army is even worse!
知道就好
Good to know you know!
回去
Get back there!
放了八路  太君找咱们算账
If we let Mr. 8 go, the Japanese will come after us.
放了太君  八路找咱们报仇
If we let the Japanese go, the 8's will come for us.
事到如今呐
Given our choices,
只有都宰了
they all have to die!
做到人不知鬼不觉
We make them all disappear,
就没人找咱们算账
and nobody will bother us.
把刀给我
Give me the knife.
不给你刀
I shall not.
有话好好说
We'll talk,
拿来
like adults.
就是不给你
Give it here! Nuh-uh.
拿来
Right now!
小戏子儿
Hey, actor!
你刚才
You were...
说的杀谁
gonna kill who?
就你还敢杀死我
Was it little old me?
小子
Tiny man,
你给我放下
put that down.
放下
Down!
你信不信我现在就炸死你
I'll blow you to smithereens, opera boy.
你不放下是不是
You're not putting it down?
你不放下我炸死你
Then it's smithereens for you!
你炸  你炸我就先炸死你
Try it and you get blown up first!
你要不炸你是孙子
Last one to blow up's a turtle!
你个臭戏子  你个下九流
You smelly opera boy! You silly bum!
下九流里老子我排第一
As bums go, I am a first-rate bum!
你丫排第八呢
And you, sir, are an eighth-rate bum!
你娘
Yo momma!..
你妈
Your mother?
你妈在坟地里生的你吧
Your mother had you in her coffin!
你打生下来那天
When you came out of her,
就让棺材盖子把脑袋给掩了不是
you cracked your head on the coffin lid, eh?
你爹
Yo daddy!..
Your father?
你爹给你洗澡的时候
When your father bathed you,
把你连洗澡水一块倒了
he threw you out with the bathwater!
把尿介子留下来养大了
He raised you on leftovers from the outhouse!
就你那尿性
That's why you
臭不要脸的
stink at insults!
举着个小二雷子
You and your land are mine,
你吓唬谁呢你
who do you think you're scaring?
你信不信我现在就拉
I will set this off right here!
你拉我也拉
Then so will l!
来呀来  来  来呀
Do it! Do it! Do it!
拉
Do it!
拉呀  拉呀
Do it! Do it!
拉起来没完了是不是
You're still doing it over there?
要打出去打
Take the rowdiness outside!
这里是饭馆
This is a restaurant!
别动  别动
Hey, don't move!
我跟你说这是我的
That's my stuff you're touching!
给我老婆
Give it here, honeybun!
这是我拿命换来的
I almost got killed getting that!
我跟你说  谁动我炸死谁啊
If anybody moves I'll blow you up!
日本人东西  别人不好拿的
We mustn't steal from the Japanese!
太君东西放我们这里绝对
Anything Japanese is safe
保管好
in my restaurant!
谁动都不成
No one gets to touch it!
要想砸箱分东西
If we're going to split the loot,
今儿这事儿
then we're going to
咱得先论清楚喽
discuss shares first!
开门开门开门
Open up! Open up!
磨叽啥呢  快点儿
What's taking you so long?! Come on!
侦缉队来了
The detectives!
站住
Freeze!
你要敢说出去我炸（弄）死你
Say anything and you're a dead man!
那箱子也得有我一份嘞
I'll have a share of what's in that case!
侦缉队
Detectives
好久不见  欢迎嘞
It's been a long time! Welcome!
你有没有看见啥可疑的人没有啊
Seen anybody suspicious 'round these parts?
什么都没看见啊
I ain't seen nothin'!
够热闹的
Quite the crowd today!
这是啥鳖孙玩意啊
Now what in a turtle's son is this?
我
Me!
是个人呐
Oh, a person!
你是哪儿来的
Where are you from?
山东的
Shandong!
Shandong?
杀猪的
He's a boar hunter.
A boar hunter?
二球
Twoball!
恁么了哥
What can I do for ya?
明白
Roger!
一个杀猪的
A boar hunter...
三炮
Bullet!
这又是啥鳖孙玩意啊
What in a turtle's son is this?
这是一头野猪
A wild boar!
野猪
A wild boar?
你去球吧
My third leg!
北平城哪儿来的野猪啊
Peking got no wild boars!
这是从山东抓过来的
He brought it from Shandong!
对  我带来的
Yes sir, I brought it!
中中中中  也是从山东来的
Gotcha gotcha it came from Shandong.
把这麻袋打开我看看
Open up this bag for me.
那可不行
No, can't do that!
这个野猪一见了光
If this pig sees light,
那扑扑楞楞的一弄起来摁不住啊
it's gonna run all over and wreck the restaurant!
是啊  这野猪会咬死人的
Yes, and wild boar bites are lethal!
咬人  我试试
They bite? Let's see!
啥玩意啊
What in tarnation?..
干啥呢这是
What are you doing?
跑了跑了跑了
It's running! It's running!
跑出来了吧
It's running!
你拦住他
Tackle it!
二流子  拦住啊
Scoundrel, stop it!
我这这  怎么拦啊
How'm I gonna stop it?
闭嘴  别管别管
Oh never mind!
我亲娘
My mother!
按住
Sit on it!
拦住拦住把它拦住
Stop it! Stop it! Tackle it!
你个鳖孙
This turtle's son!
不要跟畜生一般见识了
Fighting a pig isn't your job!
你敢碰我
Touch me again!
算了算了
Oh, forget it.
三炮  走
Bullet! Let's go!
你弄这玩意干啥呀你
What are you doing with this?
是是是是是
Yes, yes, yes.
畜生  不要理它了
It's a pig, ignore it.
不对
Hey!
你家里边
I remember.
那个傻媳妇儿呢
Where's your stupid wife?!
我老婆啊
My wife?
老婆呀
Honeybun!
客人要上楼了  赶紧出来吧
The guests want to go upstairs! Come on out!
咋回事
Folks?
人呢
Where is she?
这又是弄啥呢
What's this all about?
（欢迎光临）
(Welcome!)
这又是啥鳖孙玩意啊
What in a turtle's son is this?
这个东西就是日本女人的腰带
It's a Japanese lady belt, an obi.
啥
Huh?
就是日本女人背后背的那个袋袋
The belt Japanese ladies tie on their back!
学人家都学不像
How come you can't learn to tie it?
拿好
Take it!
一群神经病
You guys are crazy!
收队
Withdraw!
欢迎下次光临
Please come again!
华北自治政府严重敬告
The Northeast Autonomous Government reminds you!
六时已到北平城实行宵禁
After 6:00 p.m., Peking is under strict curfew!
城门禁闭  任何人等不得随意进出
City gates are closed, and none may enter,
以戒瘟疫蔓延  违者严惩
to prevent the spread of disease!
你到底行不行啊你
You gettin' tired there?
打不开我打  来来来
I'll open it if you can't.
啥玩意啊
What's that?
给我
Gimme that!
一定值很多钱
That's gotta be worth money!
老婆  你给我
Honeybun, give it here!
给我给我给我给我给我
Gimme! Gimme! Gimme! Gimme! Gimme!
我就不给  你干嘛
Not happening.
不给你
给我
- Gimme it! - Nuh-uh.
这垃圾  别人都不要
This trash? They don't want it.
够不着
You can't reach!
给我  给我看看
Gimme it! Lemme see it!
看什么看
See what?
日本字你认识吗
You read Japanese?
病菌
Germs...
虎烈拉菌
Cholera sample...
虎烈拉
Cholera!
不不不不不不不不  这这这
No nonononononono! The the the!!!!
我亲娘
Oh my!
谁都甭想走
None may leave!
今儿这事
This affair,
咱还得接茬论
we will get to the bottom of it!
菅井真一
Sugai Shinichi,
陆军中尉
lieutenant, Imperial Japanese Army.
小笠原五郎
Ogasawara Goro,
陆军军医大佐
colonel, bioweapons specialist,
北支那满洲第七百三十一部队
Japanese North China Area Army. Manchukuo Division Unit 731...
731部队
Unit 731!
我们闯大祸了
We're in big trouble!
东北那边放毒的日本子
You're the kimonos who spread germs in the Northeast!
把嘴打开
Open your mouth!
畜生
Animals!
你们已经是死人啦
You're already dead men!
还学过咱们的话
And he learned our language!
别说中国话  会有麻烦
Don't speak Chinese. It will bring trouble.
将死的倭寇给我听好喽
You're some dead kimonos, now listen up.
北平城里的虎烈拉是你们放的
You're the ones who spread cholera in Peking.
没错
That's right!
我跟你说小日本子
Guess what, sushi-eater!
军营里的兵自己都染上了
Your troops are all infected!
两位好汉  把我给放了
Countrymen! Cut me down, what say?
放了咱一块儿审审
Then let's interrogate these kimonos!
审你大爷
Interrogate my tuchus!
毒可是你带来的  你丫算胁从
You brought the poison! You're an accomplice!
太君
Officer...
爷今儿也做一回民族英雄
But today, I will be a hero!
这两孙子今儿是非杀不可
Today, I will kill these kimonos dead!
嘛呢
Excuse me?!
不给他们喝了
That's right, no water for you!
来来来  看看来
Hey! Take a look!
看看我这都什么
Look what I got!
咱是靠手艺吃饭的
I give what I take to the poor!
劫富济贫
Like Robin Hood!
你把我杀了
If you kill me,
你真成了民族败类了
you'll kill a hero of the people!
我告诉你
Now listen here!
老婆呀
Honeybun!
小子
Tiny man...
你要是不想死也成
If you don't want to die, alright.
待会儿  你也杀个日本子
You kill a kimono in a minute,
算是纳个投名状
and I might trust you.
拿着
Take this.
我当是多大点儿事呢
Wouldn't be nothin' to me!
反正死在我手底下的
These hands right here killed
也不差那么二三十个了
20 or 30 of 'em!
就他
This one!
蠢货
Fool!
我们是关东军生化专家
We're Kwantung Army doctors!
来北平专门治疗这场瘟疫的
They sent us to Peking to cure the epidemic!
赶快放人
Let us go!
该放血了
I do not see blood yet!
杀人之前是不是先考虑下后果
Perhaps we should consider the consequences first.
后果就是宰了两个日本子
The consequences are two kimonos die,
再把这毒物弄日本兵营给散喽
and we release this at their camp!
动手
Do it!
他傻
He's stupid,
你也傻啊
so you're stupid too?
戏子
Actor,
你知不知道这东西值多少钱
do you know how much money this is worth?
毒物值多少钱
How much is poison worth?
毒物不值钱  解毒的方子值钱
It's not the poison, it's the cure!
那两个人脑子里边
Somewhere in their brains
就有解毒的方子
they got the cure for this,
脑子里边的方子值钱
and that cure's worth money.
甭跟我提钱
Don't talk to me about money!
爷活的是一口气
I got the spirit in me today!
民族气
Patriotism!
吹牛到最后也不就是人气
You got nothin' but two farts in you.
就这个东西的解药方子
I could take this cure
把它鼓捣鼓捣上了锣鼓巷
and take it down to Drum & Bell Alley,
那怎么的不得卖出来一千个大洋
and I could sell it for at least 1,000 silvers!
多少
How much?
这要到鼓楼黑市卖呀
At the Gulou black market this
肯定能卖到五千块
cure would go for 5,000 silvers!
多少
How much?
要按照这么来说
Going off that,
我找道上的朋友最起码能翻个番
I can take this to a guy I know,
那就是一万大洋
and we could get 10,000!
一万
10,000!
那什么
Right, so,
爷可不是为了钱
it's not about the money,
爷是为了救天下的黎民百姓
I'm doing this to spare my people suffering!
对对对  那是那是啊
There you go, there you go...
想一块儿去了
We're thinking along the same lines!
来  这边说这边说这边说
Come on, let's talk over here. Over here.
来来来来来
Come along, come along.
上哪儿上哪儿
Where did they go?!
我们到外边说啊
Let's talk outside.
等等  等等
Wait! Wait!
来来来  过来  这边说啊
Come on... over here. Over here.
二流子
Scoundrel,
你过来干嘛  你不要走吗
why are you here? Weren't you leaving?
走干嘛
Why leave?
真是倒霉
Damn! The shame burns me.
落到这样几个无知混蛋手里
That we are in the hands of these ignorant fools
都怪大佐  我说要坐火车的
is all your fault, sir! I said we should take the train!
那我得要六十
Then I want 60%!
对不起
I'm sorry.
就你还要六
Sure you want 60%!
我问问你  就算我给你六
But even if you get your 60%,
你要再说老子
if you call me a turtle again
你有这个命花
you'll pay with your life!
老子带着太君去自首
When I tell them to seppuku
就你个首
I'll seppuku you myself!
就这么定
This is our deal:
三三三
a third, a third, a third.
一人一份
Equal shares for each.
支那人真无耻
Shinajin are shameless fools!
我们是两个人
My wife and I are two,
所以我们要分一半
so we want half.
真不要脸了你
The gall on you!
你怎么不说你全你给放走的
Why don't you say you wanted to let them go?!
料理店可是我的
The restaurant is mine!
人是我带来的
But I brought them here!
你闭嘴
Shut up!
白给你吃白给你住白给你
I gave you food and a bed for nothing!
想要我的
You want my share?
我跟你说
Listen here, son...
闭嘴
Shut up!
行行行  可别跟我聊这些
Don't talk to me about this, I can't even
气死你气死你气死你
I hope the anger tears you apart.
出来就跟我没关系
You have nothing to do with me.
闭嘴
Shut the motherlover up!
你们公母俩
You two each
得个四
get a fourth.
你我二人
We two
一人一个三
each get a third.
既然要分
If we have to split it,
就都别亏着了
let's do this fair and square-like!
升堂
Court is in session!
武威
Rise all!
对不啦
Is that right?
威武
All rise!
你可知罪
You know what you did.
个小日本子
You kimonos...
杀我们人
you killed our people,
糟蹋我们姑娘
you raped our women,
还不知足
but that's not enough?
还要放毒害我们
Now you want to poison us?
我咒你们生的孩子
I curse your children!
一辈儿比一辈儿矬
May each be more inbred than the next!
一个一个都是罗圈腿
May their legs ever be of differing sizes!
给我照实了翻
Translate that faithfully!
一字儿不落啊
Every word!
太君
Sir...
他
he...
反对日本
is against Japan.
怎么茬
Excuse me?
完了
That's it?
我这儿得吧得吧说这么多
How did I just say all that,
你怎么两句话完事儿了
and you said it in two lines?
日本话嘛  言简意赅呀
Japanese is deep and efficient.
给我往严重里说
Translate the whole thing!
蠢货
Fool!
虎烈拉早就该用在你们身上
We should have used cholera on you ages ago!
让你们所有支那狗全死光
We should have killed every one of you shinajin!
畜生
Animals!
看来
It appears
这解药的方子
you don't intend
你是不打算跟这儿说了
to give us the cure today.
是吧
Is that so?
行
Very well!
伺候着
Oblige him!
这种无赖的手法
These humiliating techniques
只会对你们支那人才有用
only work on scum like you shinajin!
来吧
Bring it on!
有朝一日时运到
The time had come to draw the sword
拔剑要斩海底蛟
and slay the vile sea-dragon!
把那瓶最高的给我
Give me the tallest bottle.
对了
Right.
半步颠
Essence of Divine Bouyancy
你这个小胡子男人
You small-moustached fool!
你们到底想干什么的
How dare you fools do this!
这样侮辱日本军人
Humiliating a Japanese officer
一定会死上十次的
will earn you ten deaths!
快放开我混蛋
Let me go, you perverted fools!
“咚”
THWACK!
“太君，加油”
Cheer up, sir!
来吧
Bring it on!
情绪
And... smile!
混蛋
Fools!
来吧
Bring it on!
笨蛋  笨蛋
Idiot! Idiot!
5小时前
5 HOURS AGO
笨蛋  笨蛋
Idiot! Idiot!
胡说  该怎么说来着
Watch your mouth. Now what's your line?
来了  来了
They're coming! They're coming!
来了
They're coming.
计划发送完毕
I've just finished sending our plan.
接到最新的命令
We received new orders.
必须要在三天之内拿到疫苗
We need to get the vaccine in three days.
现在整个华北地区
There are a million infected
已经有上百万人感染了
in the northeast,
晋察冀边区也开始有人感染
and cases appearing along the central periphery.
三天
Three days?
依我们对日本人的了解
Based on what we know
他们的顽强程度
about the Japanese,
跟缜密程度是可以想像
and how tenacious and secretive they are,
在短时间之内
in that short a time,
常规审讯肯定不会奏效
ordinary interrogation won't be effective.
我提议啊
I propose
还是按照我的方法来
that we stick to my plan.
这肯定是一台好戏
It will definitely be a good show.
好戏是需要票房的
Good shows need to sell tickets.
嘛呢
What in the name of...
咱们得为几百万人的性命负责任
We're responsible for millions of lives.
万一要是演砸了
What if we blow the part?
可就是大事
That would be very bad.
正因为这是关系到
Precisely because millions of
几百万人性命的事
lives rest on our success or failure,
所以我们才不能孤注一掷
we need more than one plan.
不让这些搞研究的人
If we don't make these researchers
放松警惕
let down their guard
我们一点机会都没有
we don't stand a chance at all.
我们是同行
I'm a scientist too.
这点我最了解
I know better than anyone.
我们最擅长的就是按逻辑对攻
We will stalemate each other with logic.
我同意
I agree.
对付书呆子  就不能按套路出牌
Cliches never work against scholars.
没听说过吗
Have you ever heard
九段围棋高手
that Level 9 go players
被街边不会下棋的人给赢了
sometimes lose to new players?
为什么呀
Do you know why?
没按照他的规矩来呀
They don't play by familiar strategies.
咱们就不按照规矩呀胡来
If we break the rules, if we confuse them,
他们乱了  咱们赢定了
then we're guaranteed to win.
我不同意
I disagree.
日本人要不吃这套怎么办
If they don't buy it, what do we do?
我还是坚持
I still like my plan.
只要抓住日本人
We just have to catch them,
就赶紧把疫苗送到解放区
and get the vaccine to the free zones.
送到边区路上至少得两天
It's at least a 2-day journey to the free zones.
时间肯定是来不及
There's not enough time.
可再这样讨论下去
And there will be even less
那就更来不及了
if we keep talking!
客人什么时候到
When do our guests arrive?
情报说是明天
The report says tomorrow.
这样
Right now,
现在正好是全城戒严没有客人
with the city under quarantine, we have no customers,
咱们就利用这个机会
and this is an opportunity.
把他们圈进咱们料理馆
We can trap them here, in the restaurant.
料理馆这么多年的改造
The modifications we've made to the place
正好可以用上
are perfect for this game.
可是我真的不会演
But I can't act!
这么多年面对客人
All these years, in front of customers,
偶尔演一下还行
I could do that performance.
可这三天
But this is three days,
我们每分每秒面对的是敌人
every second in front of the enemy!
万一有什么破绽怎么办
What if we make a mistake?
我说你们怎么都变得
When did you people turn into
跟老头老太太似的
scared old ladies?
这根本就不是在冒险
We aren't taking a risk like this!
把我说的方法
Combining my method
跟正常审讯结合到一块
with the standard interrogation methods
这只是多了一层成功的保障嘛
gives us one more chance of success!
成
Ok.
咱们就相信老二的判断
Then we'll do it your way.
不过这出戏可不好演
But this won't be an easy performance.
要想蒙住日本人
Scaring the Japanese means
咱们必须得演得特别疯狂
we have to be crazier than they are.
把你们的看家本事都亮出来吧
This role will take every skill you have.
服从命令
Those are my orders.
不讨论了
No more discussion.
准备吧
Get ready.
笨蛋  笨蛋
Idiot! Idiot!
第二日
DAY 2
太君
Officer!
我来了
It's me!
他们带的不是疫苗
That's not a vaccine they have,
肯定是原菌液
it's a germ sample.
小笠原瞬间的反应紧张极了
Ogasawara's reaction was pure terror.
既然是真的生化专家
So he really is a biologist.
可他们为什么现在带着原菌液
But why were they bringing a cholera sample
来到北平呢
to Peking?
日军
The Japanese might
可能察觉到虎烈拉病毒正在变异
have discovered a mutant strain of cholera,
所以需要研制出新的疫苗
so they wanted to research a new vaccine.
来这是做实验的
They could be here for experiments.
那也就是说
So what you're saying
我们现在即便拿到了
is even if we get the vaccine,
也只是原来疫苗的配方
it only works on the original strain.
变异只是怀疑对吧
But this mutant strain is a theory?
对
Yes.
也就是说
So you're saying
现在的疫苗还管用
the original vaccine still works?
那就必须拿下
Then we need to get it.
说说下一步
What's the next step?
下一步是厨子的苦肉计
The chef pretends to get hurt.
无论如何要让敌人相信他
We need to gain their trust
这样我们才有更大的机会
before anything else happens.
太君呐
Officer...
喝点水
Have some water.
保存点儿体力啊
Preserve your strength!
这帮家伙这么搞下去
If these fellows keep this up,
会出人命了
someone might die!
早知道这帮家伙那么歹毒
If I had known they were so vicious,
我就不要那点钱了
I never would have wanted that money!
我跟他们可不是一伙的
I'm not one of them, Officer!
你跟哪儿弄的水
Where did you get that water!
谁让你喝水了
No water for you!
厨子
Chef...
你说什么是
Tell me what you think
民族败类呀
a national disgrace is?
民族败类就是那个汉奸
A national disgrace is a Han traitor!
汉奸
Han traitor?!
汉奸  汉奸  汉奸  汉奸  汉奸
Han traitor?! Han traitor?! Han traitor?!
消消气  消消气
Calm down, calm down...
你说什么是汉奸
What's a Han traitor?
汉奸啊
A Han traitor...
就是卖国贼呀
They sell out their country!
卖国贼
卖国贼  卖国贼  卖国贼
They sell out they sell out they sell out their country!
卖国  卖国  卖国贼
卖国贼
They sell out their country!
那你说
So tell me
什么是卖国贼呀
what is selling out your country?
卖国贼呀
Well, that...
他分好多种哪
there are lots of ways!
打人不打脸的
Hit the body, not the face!
老子今天跟你拼命
Let's have at it, then!
哥  原谅你了
Okay, I forgive you.
回头咱们抽丫
We'll get him for that later.
大佐
Colonel,
您一定要坚持住
stay strong, sir.
这群蠢货只会用这样的下流方法
These fools only know how to play with us.
他们根本不懂什么叫死亡
They don't understand death.
他们只能更激励我的斗志
They only provoke me to fight harder!
住嘴
Silence.
仔细观察
Observe them.
这些人
Closely.
这不会说话
So it can speak!
我还以为是个哑巴呢
Thought we had us a mutie!
甭废话  吊起来
No more talking! String them up!
你们不要再进行这种愚蠢刑讯了
Stop this foolish torture. Or ten times worse
哪怕再加上十倍
will be done to you.
对我们也不起一点作用
This won't work on us.
你们听着
Now listen,
我们伪装到华北
we came north in disguise
就是为了避免不必要的麻烦
because we wanted to avoid unnecessary trouble.
有很多匪徒在等着我们
We would have been ambushed by bandits.
这些人都不明白
And they wouldn't understand
起
Up!
如果我们死了会产生
the terrible consequences
多么可怕的后果
our deaths would cause!
上百万人都会送命
Millions would die!
会有很多日本人死掉
Many would be Japanese,
但死的更多的是你们支那人
but many more would be shinajin like you!
他在这吧啦吧啦的
In all that jibber-jabber,
是不是已经把这人方子都给招了
did he just give away the vaccine?
厨子
Chef!
汉奸厨子
Traitor chef!
老子我在这里
I'm up here!
太君没有招
No he did not!
太君很坚强
He's so very strong!
太君说了  他们打扮成商人样子
He said they came north dressed as merchants
就是怕你们这帮歹徒不顾大局
because they were afraid of bandits like you!
这臭丫挺的
This son of a pooch!
给我升高了  吊房顶上去
Get them up there! To the roof!
我看这汉奸厨子
Let's see if this traitor chef
还有什么招伺候这俩日本子
can find a way to serve these kimonos then!
还真是在严刑拷打呀
My, but it's so brutal!
看来是在问密码
They're asking for the combination.
哥
Brother,
你恁么确定
how do you know
那人带密码的蓝箱子里
that case with the combination lock
有宝贝呀
has loot in it?
这又是啥鳖孙玩意啊
What the turtle's son is this?
这里边肯定装的是值大钱的东西
Oh, they got themselves a fancy stash in there.
那咱为嘛不进去把那箱子抢出来
How come we don't go in and take it?
立个大功
We'll solve a case.
没准还能成为侦缉队的正规队员
They might even make us full-time detectives!
鳖孙  鳖孙
Turtleson! Turtleson!
还侦缉队
Detectives?!
有了宝贝
If we sell that loot,
买它个日本联队给咱当保镖
we can hire Japanese detectives as bodyguards!
老大真有远见
Such vision, boss!
今天晚上
Tonight,
穿上夜行服带上家伙
come back dressed in black, with knives,
咱给他来个神兵天降
and we'll go in there and take our baby!
太君
Officer!
你看这啥
Look what I got!
渴不
Thirsty?
两天没喝水了
You've been 2 days with no water!
来来来
Hey! Hey!
让他们发现  就麻烦了
If they see me, it's trouble!
快整两口
Quick, drink some!
太君
Officer!
摔死丫
Drop him!
妈呀
Oh my!
还真没摔死
He's still not dead!
起来吧你
Get up!
疼
Ow!
像你这么不讲道义
Where's your sense of justice?
不讲规矩的玩意儿
Do the rules not apply to you?
我说要不然直接就给他
What do you say if I just saw
咔嚓了得了
your head off!
住着
Don't move!
其实我这么做也是为大家好
I was doing it for your own good!
太君高兴了也能给大家留条活路
If they're pleased with us, they might spare us!
汉奸婆子你给我听好喽
Traitor's wife, listen up!
你二人犯的是叛国罪
You two have betrayed your country!
这要是拉大街上去
If word of this got out on the street,
够枪毙你们十回
your neighbors would kill you on sight!
报应啊
It's karma!
报应
Karma!
老子这条腿都摔坏了
My leg was shattered in the fall.
这就是报应
That's my punishment!
好了我知道错了
I won't do it again.
晚了
Too late!
像这种祸害
Criminals like this
我跟你说就不能留根儿
have to be cut off at the root.
要不然  直接给他来个斩草除根
You want I should just cut off his root?
与子孙无关
His children are innocent!
这个样
Alright,
听我的
then how about,
死罪可免  活罪难饶
we won't kill him, but we can't let it go,
给他切几个指头豆怎么样
so I'll cut off a few toes as punishment!
等等
Wait!
老子那些钱全是你们的了
You can have my share of the money!
那成啊
That works!
那我老婆的那份
But my wife still wants her share!
还是要的哦
I still want that.
下刀
Cut his toes off!
你怎么变红了
Why did you turn red?
那个小胡子男人给我打了药
The tiny-moustached man gave me a shot.
嗓子都发不出声了
My throat's so sore I can't shout.
这样的屈辱还不如让我剖腹吧
I would rather seppuku than bear these insults!
安静下来
Quiet!
必须想办法出去
We need to think of a way out.
部队里的疫情要是不控制住
The epidemic in the army is out of control.
整个战争就会输掉
This could even cost us the war.
忍耐
Bear it!
他们已经知道我们是七三一部队的
They already know we're from Unit 731.
我们杀了那么多支那人
We've killed so many shinajin.
他们是不会放过我们的
They won't let us go.
那些都不是人
Those weren't people.
他们只是实验品
They were experimental subjects.
明白
Understood.
随便说一个配方骗他们吧
Just give them a false vaccine.
他们也许会放我们
They may let us go.
别小看他们
Don't underestimate them.
没那么简单
They're not that simple.
说什么都会杀人灭口
They'll kill us whatever we say.
所以我要想办法脱身
We must find a way to escape.
那应该怎么办
Then what should we do?
支那人最大的弱点就是不团结
The shinajin's biggest weakness is lack of unity.
他们这帮人应该
These people likely...
歹徒啊
You monsters!
哥可得急眼了
Now I'm getting mad!
我去你娘的脚
By the saints, my foot!
我的脚啊
My foot!
太君哪
Officers,
没问题  我会放了你
don't worry, I'll get you out.
你听我说
Listen to me.
现在
Right now,
重庆方面  共产党  民间团体
the Chongqing government, the Communists,
都想要疫苗配方
and everyone else wants this vaccine.
但是
But
如果没有我的话
without me,
他们得到了也没有用
they won't be able to make it.
所以
So,
如果你真的为帝国着想的话
if you truly wish to serve the Empire,
就把我放了
set me free.
皇军会给你很多的钱
The Imperial Army will give you a lot of money.
怎么样
What do you say?
那太好了
I love money!
再等几天就好了
Just give me a few more days.
还要等几天
Yes, in a few more days
到时候所有人都死了
every one of us will be dead!
是是  是  是
Yes, yes, I know, I know.
太君
Officer,
我老婆
my wife...
他们是不防着的
they haven't tied her up.
让她帮您把配方带出去
Let her take the vaccine out
然后再给钱
and bring the money back.
行吗
How's that?
小笠原五郎
Ogasawara Goro
毕业于东京帝国大学医学系
Tokyo Imperial University Medical College graduate.
之后直接进入了七三一部队
He was directly recruited by Unit 731,
专心研究霍乱病菌的凑班
where he leads research in weaponized cholera.
不就是个书呆子吗  我来
So he's a geek. He's mine.
我倒要看看
I'd like to see
秀才遇上兵
if a soldier like me
到底能出现什么状况
can outwit a geek like him.
记着啊
Remember,
我们第一步的目标不是疫苗
our primary goal isn't the vaccine,
而是无所顾忌
it's to be shameless,
什么事都干得出来
like we have no bottom line.
一定要让他们相信
We have to make them believe
我们无知无耻无谓
we're ignorant, unprincipled,
加无赖
and have no goals.
然后
Then,
让他们把警惕性放松下来
we get them to let their guard down,
寻找机会
and look for our chance.
你以为你能骗得了我吗
Do you think you can fool me?
你们都是疯子
You're all insane.
你们到底是什么人
Who are you people?
你误会了
I'm sorry, sir!
我和我太太是良民  良民  良民
My wife and I are innocent! Innocent!
还真是上阵父子兵
It's a whole family of traitors!
卖国夫妻档啊
A husband-wife traitor act!
今儿晚上得见点血啦
Someone's going to bleed tonight!
天皇陛下
Glory to the Empire!
万岁
Bonzai!
怨不得天  怨不得地
Ain't no gods to save you now!
要怨就怨你自己吧
This is what kimonos get!
时辰到
It's time!
开铡
Make the incision!
事情不会像咱们想得那么简单
It won't be as simple as we'd thought.
小笠原是不会轻易交出疫苗的
Ogasawara won't give up the vaccine that easily.
或许我们想复杂了
Or maybe we're making this complicated.
是个人都有极限
Everyone has their limits.
你说咱们是不是还
Maybe we should take
缺点火候应该再加把劲
the intensity up a notch.
准备假铡刀吧
Get fake blood and a blade ready.
这时候真见点血  也许管用
Seeing a little blood might move things along.
甲贺派忍者菅井来也
I am Sugai, ninja of the Koga clan!
这孙子嘿
This turtleson!
是不是疯了
He's turtling crazy!
我就给他上了点药
I just gave him a little shot!
按理说不应该是这个疗效
The medicine shouldn't work that well!
别动别动别动
Don't move don't move don't move...
息怒息怒息怒
Calm down! Calm down!
畜生  来吧
Animals! BRING IT ON!!
我亲娘
Oh my!
这个药效确实有点出乎意料
That medicine worked way better than I thought!
混蛋
Fools!
确定出菅井真一的真实身份了吗
Have you confirmed Sugai Shinichi's identity?
这个是昭和十一年
In 1937, in Kansai,
关西地区一个地下组织的
an underground children's organization
童子纹身
marked members like this.
就从这个纹身来看
From the tattoo alone,
这个菅井
we know Sugai
不可能有帝国大学的经历
never went to the Imperial University.
那由此可以确定那个小笠原
And from that, we know this Ogasawara
就是东北七三一细菌部队
is from Unit 731's germ warfare department,
人体实验的参与者
a perpetrator of experiments on humans.
刚才是抓马猴子
They were just trying to catch an orangutang,
现在
and now
咋又出来个日本人了
we got more Japanese down there!
哥
Boss,
他们这干嘛呢
what are they doing?
别闹
Quiet!
我思考思考
I gotta think!
开门
Open up!
得了  汉奸厨子
Ok, traitor chef!
起来吧 起来吧
Get up! Get up!
下边有你活了
You got a customer!
老子今天不干活了
I'm off work today!
有种你自己去接待了
Why don't you go answer the door?
咱谁跟谁都没仇  对不对
We're all friends here, ain't we?
再者说了  跟钱也没仇  是不是
And we all want the money, right?
大哥
Come on.
是五十岚大尉呀
Captain Igarashi!
还是不营业吗
Not open today?
对  今天不营业
No, not today.
但是
But
查了一天的案子
I have been on cases all day.
我很累呀
I'm very tired.
是  是
Yes, yes.
因为有两个专家被绑架了
Because two experts were kidnapped.
大尉
Captain.
知道了
I know.
这里我很熟
They're friends here.
只剩下两条鱼了
Only two fish left.
真是失望啊
That's a disappointment.
现在封城封得那么厉害
The quarantine is very strict.
从天津来的鱼呀都运不过来了
My suppliers in Tianjin can't get through.
不过到底是河豚啊
But these are blowfish.
可以吃一条吗
May I have one?
拜托了
Please.
白川
Shirakawa,
这是我们的地万
they're friendly here.
你过来坐下吧
Come take a seat.
请
Enjoy.
（可能要暴露了  准备干掉他们）
(We're risking exposure. Be ready to eliminate them.)
（明白）
(Understood.)
白川
Shirakawa,
干什么呢  赶快过来
what are you doing? Get over here.
河豚已经准备好了
The fugu is ready.
你该不会是不敢吃河豚吧
Don't tell me you're too scared!
（现在动手吗）
(Should we kill them now?)
这个
This...
这个是什么呀
What is this?
这个
This...
河豚鱼肝
is blowfish liver!
剧毒
It's poison!
这也是剧毒的吧
Is this poison too?
剧毒
Yes, poison!
试试看看
Let's see how poisonous!
别扎别扎别扎
Don't poke it, no...
不要不要  不要
Don't! Don't!
万一真出意外怎么办
What if something happens?
见机行事
We'll play it by ear.
能有什么事
What could happen?
逢山开路  遇水搭桥呗
We'll improvise our way out.
还真别说
And you know what?
这时候要是真出点事
If something does happen at that point,
还真不一定是个坏事
it might not be a bad thing.
（审讯陷入僵局）
(Interrogation is a dead end.)
（现在引诱日本人包围我们）
(Have them make the Japanese surround us.)
（促使人质出手）
(The hostages will act.)
（好）
(Okay.)
（快写  我争取带出去）
(Write the note, I'll take it out.)
还没摔死丫
You're still alive up there?!
混蛋
Fool!
写什么
Write what?
悍匪劫我母女上山寨
Bandits stole my wife and daughter to their lair.
母弱女病实不奈
My wife is weak, daughter sick, they cannot fight.
好汉围观不出手
Heroes look on, but yet none act.
恨无义士今何在
Who are these unjust, hateful warriors?
人间万事无常理
There is no justice is men's affairs.
什么人
Who is this?
谁与子龙论成败
Who will speak with Zilong of victory and defeat?
转过来
Turn around!
你喜欢玩儿这个呀
So you know how to use this?
比试比试
Let's see how good you are.
我说
I said,
比试比试呀
let's see how good you are.
听见了没有
Did you hear me?
来呀
Come on!
蠢货
Fool!
畜生
Animal!
你死了
You're dead!
这是什么东西呀
What in tarnation is this?
我们新请过来的花旦
Our new female role actor.
真是太丑了
He's hideous.
戏好啊
But he's good!
这帮日本人是假的
I say those Japanese are fake.
蓝箱子
And the case,
他们已经私吞了
they already got it open.
正在喝庆功酒呢
They're celebrating right now.
让我来射他们一箭
Let's drop an arrow in there
我探探底细
and see who's who!
你个鳖孙
You turtle's son!
没话传过去你射啥射
You shot without a letter!
给我
Give it here!
她是谁
Who is she?
太君  我老婆  老婆
Officer, my wife, my wife...
老婆
Your wife?
我们是良民来的
We're innocent, we're good people.
五十岚大尉晓得我们的
Captain Igarashi knows us.
这位是我们店里的头牌花旦
This is our female role actor.
跟太君打个招呼
Say hello to the nice man.
去嘛
Go!
这是个什么东西
What is going on here?
这是什么
What's this?
离开  不然你们都会死在这里
LEAVE NOW, OR YOU ALL WILL DIE HERE.
大尉
Captain,
时间太晚了
it's getting late.
你别管
So what?
大尉
Captain,
该回去了
we should go.
钱
The money,
忘带了
we forgot.
算我们请客好了
Then it's on the house.
不行
No.
钱一定要给
We have to pay you.
老板娘跟我去取
Your wife will come with us to get it.
稍等一下
Wait!
老婆
Honeybun,
外面风大
it's cold outside.
跑了几个
They're running away!
哥  回家
Boss, let's go home!
回啥家
Home my tuchus!
寻宝
Let's get the loot!
你们
Who
到底是
are
什么人
you people?
匪徒挟持  菌液被掠
I'VE BEEN KIDNAPPED, THEY HAVE THE CHOLERA SAMPLE.
攻击慎重  小笠原五郎
ATTACK WITH CAUTION. OGASAWARA GORO.
这么干太冒险了
This is too dangerous!
你有多大把握
How do you know this will work?
我的把握是
What I'm sure of
一旦日本人包围我们
is that once the Japanese surround us,
他们一定会通过他们军队
they will use some sort of code
特有的方式
to make Ogasawara transmit
让小笠原传递疫苗元素构成
the formula for the vaccine,
只要传递  我们就有机会截获
and once they do, we can intercept.
这只是你的猜测
That's only a guess.
现在暴露已成事实
That we're exposed is a fact!
万一你这招不管用  怎么办
If this doesn't work, what then?
不行的哥
No, boss,
别让我先下去
don't make me go down there.
下去
Get down there!
你下去
别  别  哥
No, don't! Boss! No!
下去
Get down there!
别别  哥  别呀哥
No, don't! Boss! No!
下去吧你
Get down there!
二球
Twoball?
路还好是吧
Was it a pleasant journey?
哥
Boss...
来吧
Coast clear...
这是到目前能想到的最好的方式
That's the best thing I can think of right now.
不然呢
What else is there?
不管怎么说
No matter what,
到手的原液不能再丢掉
we can't lose the original sample again.
现在当务之急
Our first job is
是马上带着原液和人质
to get the sample and the hostage
迅速撤到解放区
to the free zone.
红英怎么办
What about Hongying?
咱们走了  红英怎么办
If we go, what happens to her?
就算咱们把原液送到解放区
Even if we get the sample to the free zone,
可是没有配方
we don't have a vaccine!
又有什么用
What good is that?
这么好的机会如果耽误了
If we waste the opportunity we have now,
浪费的不只是时间
we're not just wasting time!
还会害死更多的人
Even more people will die!
我认为他说得对
I think he's right.
如果我们带走人质
If we take him away,
小笠原就会知道我们的真实身份
Ogasawara will know who we are.
如果他到死
If he decides
都不肯说一句实话的话
to take his secret to the grave,
我们就一点办法都没有了
there's nothing we can do.
所以只要留下  我们就还有机会
The only chance we have is to stay here.
相信我
Trust me.
再等一天
I just need one more day.
不能前功尽弃呀
We can't give up now.
哥
Boss!
俺卡住了
I'm stuck!
你个鳖孙
You turtleson!
你钻个烟囱都钻不好
You can't even get down a fireplace?!
你就搁上边放风
Then get back up there and stay on lookout!
醒球
Turdball!
二球  干正事  走
Twoball, let's get to work.
好
Fine.
就一天
One more day.
到明天晚上
By tomorrow night,
如果事情进展得还不顺利
if things aren't going our way,
你们俩是这方面的专家
you two are the experts,
带着人质和原液
you take the hostage and the sample,
撤离到解放区
and get to the free zone.
要走你们两个走
You two should go.
我死也要跟红英死在一起
If I have to die, I'll die with Hongying.
不争了
Enough.
明天会很难
Tomorrow will be difficult.
日军一定会杀进来
The Japanese will come charging in,
必是一场恶战
and it will be an ugly fight.
谁活下来
Whoever's left alive
谁去解放区
can go to the free zone.
来
Now,
准备吧
get ready!
“可找着你了”  宝贝
That's my baby!
“哥  救我啊”  我被红人钉小车里了
The red man nailed me in a box! Boss, help me!
“这帮人惹不起”  各自保重吧
Every man for himself! These guys are dangerous!
中井联队前进
Nakai Squadron, advance!
全速  快点
Full speed ahead!
齐藤联队全速前进
Saito Squadron, advance! Full speed!
木下联队前进  快点
Kinoshita Squadron, advance! Speed!
快点  别磨蹭
Get a move on! No lagging!
第三天
DAY 3
赶快围住  没时间了
Get this building surrounded! There's no time!
长官马上到
The commander will be here soon!
快点  你们上楼
Hurry up! Get upstairs!
别磨蹭  赶快上楼
No lollygagging! Up the stairs!
快点  没时间了
Hurry up! There's no time!
高木联队已经到位
Takagi Squadron is in position!
木下联队攻击准备就绪
Kinoshita Squadron is ready to attack!
快  没时间了
Hurry! There's no time!
长官马上就要到了
The commander is almost here!
后面快点
In the back, hurry up!
快点快点
Hurry! Move!
你在干嘛  赶快行动
What are you doing? Get to work!
中佐
Lieutenant Colonel!
中佐  报告  料理店已完成包围
Lieutenant Colonel, reporting! The restaurant is surrounded!
柳田
Yanagida!
准备吧
Get ready.
这孙子
Look at this guy!
溜溜折腾了一宿
He's been swinging around all night!
我说
Hey,
你年轻  你逮他去
you're young, you catch him.
我跟这儿看着汉奸
I'll watch the traitor chef.
行了行了
Leave it alone.
我看他根本没打算出去
I don't think he wants to leave.
让他再飞会儿吧
Let him fly for a while.
来吧
BRING IT ON!!
请开门
Open the door.
我是大日本国
I represent the Empire
陆军华北驻屯军的代表
of Japan's Kwantung North China Army.
我来谈判
I'm here to negotiate.
什么军
What army?
什么判
Negotiate what?
你们已经被包围
You are surrounded.
你们的罪行我们都知道了
We're fully aware of your crimes.
我跟你说
Then listen here!
别吓唬人啊
Don't try nothin' funny!
俺这里边
In here,
地雷炸弹手榴弹什么都有
we got land mines, bombs, grenades, everything!
要进来就炸了它
Try to come in, you get blown up!
我只是来谈判的
I'm only here to negotiate.
只有我一个人进来
I am alone.
你们可以放心
There's nothing to worry about.
请开门
Please open the door.
可以啊
Look at that!
敢一个人儿进来
She really came in alone!
华北驻屯军军方命令
The Kwantung North China Army
你们必须立刻交出武器
orders you to hand over your weapons immediately,
放了被扣押的日本人
and release the Japanese you have captive.
军方会酌情给你们
If you do,
最体面的结局
we are prepared to be lenient.
削死你  过来过来
Time to clean your clock! Come here!
过来
Get back here!
请回答
Please answer.
要不然
How about
这个样你看好不好
we do it like this?
你先给俺一万块现大洋
First, you give me 10,000 silvers.
人  俺先带走
Then I take the hostage and go.
不过你放心
But don't you worry.
到时候肯定给你放回来
On the road I'll send him right back to you.
我没有做决定的权限
I don't have the right to make decisions.
我会转达你们的要求
I will pass on your demands.
但我必须先见到人质
But first I must see the hostage
确定人质的安全
to confirm his safety.
大佐
Colonel!
不要过来
Don't come any closer!
你是哪个部队的
What unit are you?
我是
I am
华北驻屯
Japanese North China Area Army,
步兵混成旅团通信团机要员小队长
signals and communications officer and squad commander,
柳田樱
Yanagida Sakura.
军衔是
Rank,
少尉
second lieutenant.
为什么
Why do you
你会说中文
know Chinese?
我曾经在燕京大学读过书
I studied at Yenching University.
河边将军命令你
General Kawabe orders you
把配方用电码方式告诉我
to tell me the vaccine formula by code.
军中疫情
The epidemic among
已经很危急了
the troops has reached a crisis point.
不行
No.
那个厨子懂日语
That chef speaks Japanese,
不能用电码
code isn't safe.
你会说德语吗
Can you speak German?
对不起
I'm sorry.
我不知道您在说什么
I don't understand what you said.
行了
Alright.
回去告诉将军
Inform the general:
正午
Noon,
摩斯方式
Morse code.
快点
Move!
第八中队到第一地点
Squad 8 is at location 1!
第六中队抵达指定地点
Squad 6 is at the specified location!
第五中队抵达第二地点
Squad 5 is at location 2!
快点
Move!
准备攻击前方
Prepare attack formation!
玩真的了
It got real.
真麻烦
This is annoying.
直接冲进去不就行了吗
Why don't we just charge in and end it?
被绑架的是最重要的专家
They kidnapped a very important expert.
绝对不能让他死掉
We cannot allow him to die.
老婆呀  你可遭老罪了
Honeybun! Oh, you poor thing.
什么事啊老婆
What is it, honeybun?
使用JN-25B编译信号
USE CYPHER JN-25B.
这汉奸婆子嘿
The traitor's wife,
到了把咱们爷们给卖了
here to sell us out!
你瞅瞅
Look at that!
忘了你不会说话
I forgot you can't talk!
一早开头就应该崩了你们俩
I should have stoved you two in this morning!
把手举起来  别动
Now hands up! Don't move!
跑
Run!
嘛呢
Excuse me!
赶紧溜
Now hurry!
站住
Get back here!
丑老婆子赶紧去
Run away, honeybun!
站住
Hold still!
走走走走
Let's get out of here!
我真开枪了啊
I'll really shoot!
别别别  什么事都好说
No! No! Let's just talk!
汉奸厨子  汉奸婆子
Traitor chef! Traitor's wife!
再跑我可真开枪了
Keep running and I'll shoot!
听见没有
Did you hear me?
他们要用JN-25B传递密码
They're using cypher JN-25B.
咱们用老办法
Let's do the usual. Get a blood pack.
拿血包
They won't hold still!
我瞧瞧  拼命
Look at this!
你看这个
He's in there,
扔在那里  嘴被堵着
and his mouth is gagged,
所以说只要看清楚动作就可以了
so you just have to watch his motions.
明白
Got it!
来来来来
Hey hey hey hey!
到手的银子眼看就到手
We almost had the silver,
你丫想独吞  没门
and you want it for yourself? No way!
汉奸婆子给我听着
Traitor's wife,
看你也不是好东西
one look and I knew you were no good!
你还往哪儿躲
Where do you think you'll hide?
我看你能躲哪儿去
Let go of me! Let go!
松开快滚松开快
Let's see where you try to hide!
爷给你表演表演
Now I'm gonna give you a show!
要追爷  爷可真跟你玩命
Chase me and I'll show you what for!
老子跟他拼命了
I'll show him what for!
今儿个把话给我说清楚喽
You're explaining this to me right now!
二流子那边堵着他
Scoundrel, go stop him!
我瞧瞧
I'm going!
跑  我看你往哪儿跑
There's nowhere you can run!
快点给捕住她
Pin her down!
跑跑跑跑跑
Try to run! Try to run!
站着别动啊
Now nobody moves!
我弄不死你我
You think I won't kill you?
事情既然已经到了这个地步
Think about your odds, gentlemen!
不如你们两个投降好了
All you can do now is surrender!
到时候跟太君商量商量
Tell the Japanese what you did,
还能够从轻发落
and maybe they'll go easy on you!
你放屁
My tuchus!
反正老子是不出去了
I know I ain't leaving!
就算是小鬼子敢进来
Let 'em try to come in here!
进来我就拉弦儿
When they get in here,
拉了弦儿大不了轰一声
I'll pull the string, and boom!
大家同归于尽  一了百了
We all go up in flames!
中国人不杀中国人
Chinese don't kill Chinese.
你也算中国人
You still think you're Chinese?
二流子
Scoundrel,
你先下手
you go first!
手起刀落
Bring your knife down,
咔嚓一声
we'll hear a wet crack,
汉奸厨子脑袋就落地了
then the traitor chef's head rolls!
我看行
Sounds good!
对了
And then,
你过会儿也拿枪管
you take your gun barrel,
直接顶着他天灵盖子上
stick it right up his neck,
过会儿  叭的一枪
get it on there, pull the trigger,
一下  天灵盖就给掀开
then blam! His head opens up
里边脑浆撒成一地
and his brains spill out!
得嘞
Alright!
我就汉奸厨子了啊
The traitor chef is mine!
我就这个汉奸婆子了
The traitor's wife is mine!
我喊一二三
I'll shout 1, 2, 3...
来
Here we go...
一
1...
二
2...
三
3...
把老子逼急了
Now you made me mad!
老子一枪解决你们两个人
Now I'm gonna have to kill you!
你这辱没祖先的玩意儿
You're an insult to your ancestors!
看准了
She's in my sights!
老婆
Honeybun!
我亲娘
Oh my!
真闹出人命来了
We really killed somebody!
你真开枪啊  孙子
You shot your own wife?!
这回算崴了泥了
Now this is bad!
两国交战还不斩来使呢
Countries at war don't kill ambassadors!
咱把人日本人
Now we just killed
派来送信儿的给杀了
the Japanese messenger.
这不绝了人后路吗
We just cut off our backup plan!
这倒霉催的我跟你说
This is no good at all!
就咱这几块料还用这么大阵势
And they got all those guys outside, for us!
往上一点
Up a little.
侧放
To the side.
肯定报复咱
We have to answer that!
这要是杀进来
If they come in here,
能有咱好
we'll give 'em a show.
擎等着死也不是法儿
But waiting for it ain't no way to die!
得嘞  咱也亮亮家伙
So let's light this sucker up!
一切就绪，随时准备疫苗配方
PREPARE TO RECEIVE TRANSMISSION OF VACCINE
请迅速通报疫苗配方
BEGIN TRANSMISSION OF VACCINE FORMULA
媳妇哎
Honeybun,
你死得好惨哎
why did you have to die like this?
死得好哎
She died right!
回等待会日本子杀进来
Once those kimonos come in here,
什么辣椒水啊老虎凳啊
they'll have pepper spray, the rack,
大铁钳子拔指甲
pliers for our fingernails,
挨个伺候咱们
all that waiting for us!
有信号了
Receiving signal!
大佐开始传送了
The colonel is transmitting!
信号接收完毕
Signal received!
老婆哎  你死得好惨哎
Honeybun, why did you have to die like this?
怎么样  记住了吗
Well? Did you get it?
密码本呢
Where's the code book?
上楼
Upstairs.
有了
Got it.
抗体的元素表有了
We have the antibody formula!
别急
Not yet.
等我验证完了再说
Celebrate once we know it works.
将军阁下
General!
情况怎么样
What's the situation?
经过检验
Our test results show
这个疫苗
this vaccine
确认无效
is ineffective.
强攻夺人
Go in and get the man!
命令敢死队
Tell the strike team
要把小笠原大佐活着带回来
to bring Ogasawara out alive!
我们是来感谢你的
We're here to thank you
顺便跟你道个别
and to say farewell.
原来如此
So that was your plan.
没想到你懂中国话啊
I didn't expect you could speak Chinese.
我没想到的事情显然更多
I think I'm more surprised than you.
看样子
I suppose
你们已经破译了疫苗的构成
you already know the vaccine formula.
一字不落
Every letter.
但是
But
那只是一种想法
it's just an idea.
还需要试验
It needs lab work
更需要临床证明
and patient testing.
这屋里
In this room,
研究细菌学的专家
you're not the
可不止你一个
only microbiologist.
想不到
I didn't expect
支那人里
you shinajin could
也有这么聪明的
be so smart.
你错了
You're wrong.
在中国人里
As Chinese people go,
我们
we, actually,
算是笨的
are pretty stupid.
别用枪
No guns!
安全地把大佐救回来
Bring the colonel back safely.
天皇陛下万岁
Glory to the Empire! Bonzai!
千万安全送到
Make sure it arrives safely.
给老师长带个好
And tell the old professor I said hi.
让那边抓紧做培养液
Have them get a culture ready,
再多准备点棉絮
and incubate it on cotton balls.
等实验结果一出来
Once the experiments prove it works,
正好赶上风季你们把疫苗随风散出去
it's the windy season, so disperse it aerially,
能救很多人
and you'll save a lot of people.
那边条件肯定艰苦
Conditions aren't good in the free zone,
但好歹能安定下来
but thankfully this is taken care of.
你以后自己一个人的时候
When you're out there alone,
肯定还会碰到很多危险
it'll be dangerous,
千万要小心
so be careful.
别说了
Don't say that.
只要你们动作快
If you move fast,
就不会有事
there won't be any problems.
你可别
So don't...
别随便就这么死了
Don't say your goodbyes yet.
驻屯军部命令
Army command orders:
还有最后一个小时
you have one hour!
如再见不到人质
If the hostages are not released,
准备抢攻夺人，请大佐阁下尽力自保
WE ARE PREPARING TO RAID THE BUILDING.
将武力强攻这地方
we will enter the building by force!
驻屯军部命令
Army command orders:
还有最后一个小时
you have one hour!
如再见不到人质
If the hostages are not released,
将武力强攻这地方
we will enter the building by force!
驻屯军部命令
Army command orders:
还有最后一个小时
you have one hour!
如再见不到人质
If the hostages are not released...
这傻媳妇还真能
This stupid wife ain't so stupid!
火里边也能出去
She can even get out through fire!
驻屯军部命令
Army command orders:
还有最后一个小时
you have one hour!
如再见不到人质
If the hostages are not released,
将武力强攻这地方
we will enter the building by force!
疫苗只对原菌液有用
The vaccine works against the original strain.
对变异菌
Against the mutant strain,
没有任何效果
it's completely useless.
我试验了很多次
I repeated the experiment many times.
根本没用
It doesn't work.
敢死队  集合
Strike team, attention!
快  敢死队前进五十米
Quickly! Advance 50 meters!
成攻击队形
Assume attack positions.
日本人已经成攻击队形
They're in attack positions.
我们没有多少时间了
We don't have much time.
你们说呢
Any thoughts?
得给红英留点时间
We need to buy Hongying some time.
不管怎么说
No matter what else,
她这次回去我们还有一线希望
if she makes it back, we still have some hope.
干吧
Let's do this!
一
1,
二
2,
三
3!
一群神经病
A bunch of turtlin' madmen!
鳖孙
Turtleson!
鳖孙玩意
Turtlin' son of a pooch!
还会火攻
Trying to kill me with fire?!
谁
Who was that?
你这鳖孙
You turtleson!
鳖孙  别动我宝贝
Turtleson! Don't touch my loot!
来吧
Bring it on!
里面发生了爆炸
There was an explosion inside!
大佐恐有危险
The colonel may be in danger!
我们提前进攻
The attack begins now!
敢死队  进攻
Strike team, advance!
里面开枪  部队进攻
Gunfire inside! Soldiers, advance!
记住将军的命令
Remember the general's orders!
慎重射击
Fire carefully!
一定要把大佐救出去
We need the colonel alive!
他没弹药了  集合
He's out of ammunition! Assemble!
瞄准
Take aim!
准备射击
Prepare to fire!
命令
Orders!
第一部队前进
Team 1, advance!
不要动
Don't move!
前进
Advance!
围住他们
Surround him!
前进
Advance!
停下来
Stop!
这里有虎烈拉变异菌
This is the mutant cholera!
攻击这里已经没用了
Continuing the attack is pointless.
别管他
Ignore him.
前进
Advance!
这是真的变异菌液
This is the mutant strain!
赶快撤退
Retreat, now!
你们会感染的
They'll be infected!
撤退
Retreat!
全体后撤
Full retreat!
怎么了  发生什么了
What's going on? What happened?
到底怎么回事了  怎么了
What happened in there?
两小时后
TWO HOURS LATER
准备攻击
Prepare to fire!
发射
Fire!
爆炸前
BEFORE THE EXPLOSION
其实
You know,
不需要再做下去了
this is pointless.
我们都已经感染了致命的病菌
We're infected with a lethal disease.
马上就会死了的
We're all dead within a few hours.
配方为什么会无效
Why doesn't the vaccine work?
细菌是你研制的
You created the germs.
病菌发生了变异
The germs mutated.
但是没有相应的对策
We didn't have a plan ready.
只有一种猜想
I only have an idea
也许可以抑制
that might cure it.
反正大家都得死
Given that we're all going to die,
现在
at this point,
可不可以说说你的那个猜想
could you tell us about your idea?
你我的失败已经注定了
You are doomed to failure,
所以说给你们并无妨
so I suppose there's nothing stopping me.
但是即便我说了
But even if I do tell you,
你们也不明白
you wouldn't understand.
几个月前
Several months ago,
德国人刚刚合成了一种单晶体
the Germans synthesized a type of monocrystal
对治疗霍乱有很大的作用
that is very effective in curing cholera.
但是在东亚因为没有实物
But the substance doesn't exist in Asia,
听以没有临床试验
so no clinical trials were conducted.
继续问
Keep asking.
单晶体
A monocrystal? The substance?
实物
Salamanderin.
蝾螈毒素
Salamander toxin.
你会讲德语吗
You speak German?
37年我在莱比锡大学
In 1937 I spent two years
进修了两年医学
at Leipzig studying medicine.
我的德语比日语好的多
My German is better than my Japanese.
你们
You know,
真是太可惜了
I almost pity you.
分子结构
Molecular structure.
蝾螈
A salamander?
是种动物吧
What kind of salamander?
生长在南美洲的一种
A rainforest species
四脚爬行动物
from South America.
体液剧毒
Its toxin is lethal.
它的构成成分
And its molecular structure,
据医学界传说
according to medical legend,
可以抑制虎烈拉病菌
can suppress cholera bacteria.
咱们都是为这狗屁任务而来
We're all here for this stupid mission,
也都是为这狗屁任务而死
and we're all going to die for this stupid mission.
如果这狗屁疫苗
If we don't even know
到死都不知道是什么的话
what this stupid vaccine is before we die,
你觉得冤吗
will you die happy?
我说了也没用
Even if I tell you, it doesn't matter.
其实现在亚洲
Right now, in Asia,
根本没有这种动物的原体
not a single specimen exists.
除非按分子式做实验
The only way is to synthesize it.
什么分子式
What's the molecular structure?
你懂吗
Would you understand?
不懂
No.
C…
C...
11…
11...
H…
H...
17…
17...
N…
N...
对不起
I'm sorry.
后面的  我也不记得了
I don't remember the rest.
时间
More time!
行了
Alright.
咱们几个去收拾收拾
Let's clean ourselves up.
死也得死出点儿样来
Let's try and die with some dignity.
马上就要见爹娘了
We're about to meet our parents.
咱们得利利落落精精神神的
We ought to have clear minds and clean hearts.
您那儿有什么规矩
Do you have any last rites
我这儿能帮衬的吗
I can help you with?
这个样子
It's like this,
我们日本人是要剖腹的
in Japan, we commit seppuku.
那是很隆重的仪式
It's a very important ritual.
可惜呀
It's a shame.
你们的人恐怕
I'm afraid your people
不会给你这个时间了吧
won't give you enough time for that.
他们会给的
They will.
因为在日本
Because in Japan,
死亡是一件很神圣的事
death is a sacred thing.
请将最后的毁灭延时一小时
PLEASE EXTEND THE DEMOLITION BY ONE HOUR
信号接收完毕
Signal received.
两小时
TWO HOURS
小笠原五郎
Ogasawara Goro
希望完成剖腹仪式
wishes to commit seppuku.
请将最后爆炸的时间
He requests the demolition to be delayed for
拖延两个小时
another two hours.
请开门
Open the door.
我是大日本国
I represent the Empire
陆军华北驻屯军的代表
of Japan's Kwantung North China Army.
我来谈判
I'm here to negotiate.
（没想到是你们）
(I never imagined it was you.)
（十年一别）
(It's been 10 years.)
（想不到再见已是敌人）
(Who knew we'd become enemies?)
（请别这么说  我跟你一样）
(Don't say that. Just like you,)
（我也不能背叛自己的民族）
(I can't betray my own people.)
（为什么要这么傻）
(Why are you being so stupid?)
（会送命的）
(This is suicide.)
（为了同胞的生命）
(For the lives of our people.)
（我不会揭穿你们的身份）
(I won't tell them who you are.)
（我能帮助你们多争取一点时间）
(I'll try to buy you some extra time.)
将军阁下
General,
船尻连队又发现九名士兵感染
the Funajiri Squadron has discovered 9 more infected soldiers.
疫情已难以控制
The epidemic is out of control, sir.
命令患病士兵全部玉碎
Order the infected to seppuku.
不需要再营救小笠原了
We don't need to rescue Ogasawara anymore.
两个小时后炸掉这个地方
In two hours, bomb this place to the ground!
是
Yes, sir!
剖腹
Seppuku
开始
begins now!
天皇陛下
Glory to the Empire!
万岁
Bonzai!
天皇陛下万岁
Glory to the Empire! Bonzai!
驻屯军部命令
Army command orders:
最后十分钟
you have 10 more minutes!
如果再见不到人质
If the hostage is not released,
将彻底摧毁这地方
we will destroy the building!
驻屯军部命令
Army command orders:
最后十分钟
you have 10 more minutes!
如果再见不到人质
If the hostage is not released,
将彻底摧毁这地方
we will destroy the building!
驻屯军部命令
Army command orders:
最后十分钟
you have 10 more minutes!
如果再见不到人质
If the hostage is not released,
将彻底摧毁这地方
we will destroy the building!
驻屯军部命令
Army command orders...
老二
Second,
咱们都感染了变异菌
we're infected with the mutant strain.
就别出去祸害人了
Don't hurt yourself anymore.
要死咱们哥几个一块死
Let's die together, like brothers.
你拿着河豚肝干什么呀
What are you doing with that blowfish liver?
老二想干嘛
Second, what are you doing?
你知道这河豚鱼肝
You know blowfish liver
几秒钟就能麻痹你的神经
paralyzes you in seconds
十几分钟你就可以死
and kills you within 10 minutes!
我比你知道
I know better than you.
不然呢
Otherwise,
再撑几个小时
I might last a few more hours,
或者熬到明天
or even until tomorrow,
大家一块死
and die with you.
之前
But before,
我用河豚毒素做武器的时候
when I researched tetrodotoxin as a weapon,
偶然间发现
I accidentally discovered that its molecular structure
它跟蝾螈毒素的分子结构很像
was very close to salamander toxin.
试试吧
Let's try it.
或许
Maybe
能救大家一命
it will save all our lives.
老二老三红英
Brothers, Hongying,
这屋里我年龄最大
I'm the oldest one here,
我来做这个实验
so I'll be the experiment.
老大  你听我说
No, listen to me...
红英
Hongying!
咱们几个当中
Of all of us...
你松开
Let go!
我最没用
I'm the most useless!
红英
Hongying!
老三
third
你别动
Don't move!
老三你给我放开
Let go of me!
放开
Let go!
红英
Hongying!
听话  老三
Listen!
别急
Calm down.
我们还有下辈子
We still have the next life.
老三
Hey,
还有条河豚呢
there's one more blowfish.
有人出来了
Someone came out!
罪犯听好
Criminal suspect!
站在原地不要移动
Stay where you are, do not move!
听候我们的命令
Wait for our orders!
有敌人出现
One of them came out!
不要开枪
Don't shoot!
都别动
Nobody moves!
听候我们的命令
Wait for our orders!
罪犯听好
Criminal suspect!
站在原地不要移动
Stay where you are, do not move!
听候我们的命令
Wait for our orders!
再重复一遍
I repeat!
罪犯听好
Criminal suspect!
站在原地不要移动
Stay where you are, do not move!
听候我们的命令
Wait for our orders!
（保佑你）
(Bless you.)
时间到了
It's time.
炮兵队
Mortar team!
射击
Fire!
报告将军
General, reporting!
大佐的尸体已经找到
We have located the colonel's corpse.
第八天
DAY 8
虎烈拉瘟疫于北平，悄然消退…
The cholera epidemic receded in Peking
无人知其原因…
for unknown reasons.
于是，人们把提前到来的柳絮
The city's residents saw the willow catkins that year
当成上天开恩的信号
as a sign of heaven's mercy.
戏子  本名周一桐
Actor. Name: Zhou Yitong.
生于1909年  卒于1976年
Born in 1909. Died in 1976.
燕京大学机械工程系毕业
Later worked at the State Commission of Science,  Technology, and Industry.
后任职于国家科工委
Graduate of Yenching University Engineering College.
痞子  本名李芳之
Scoundrel. Name: Li Fangzhi.
生于1913年  卒于1984年
Born in 1913. Died in 1984.
燕京大学生物系毕业
Later worked at Southwestern University.
后就职于西南大学
Graduate of Yenching University Biology College.
厨子  本名刘祖鸣
Chef. Name: Liu Zuming.
生于1914年  卒于1995年
Born in 1914. Died in 1995.
燕京大学医学系毕业
Later lived in the USA.
后生活于美国
Graduate of Yenching University Medical College.
老板娘  本名武红英
Proprietress. Name: Wu Hongying.
生于1912年 卒于1995年
Born in 1912. Died in 1995.
燕京大学新闻系毕业
Married to Liu Zuming.
与刘祖鸣婚姻至1995年寿终
Graduate of Yenching University News College.
这出戏可不好演
This won't be an easy role.
把你们的绝活都拿出来吧
It's going to take every skill you have.
老三
Third,
明天开始你就是真正的厨子
tomorrow you become an actual chef.
欢迎光临
Welcome!
红英继续扮哑巴
Hongying will continue to play a mute.
那
Which
老二呢
leaves you...
这你就不用操心了
Don't worry about that!
我肯定没有问题啊
I got this down!
燕京大学入校留影
Yenching University School Enrollment
民国二十一年八月二十八日上午十时
10:00 A.M., August 28th, 1932
刘祖鸣二十周岁生日聚会留影
Liu Zuming's 20th Birthday Party
民国二十三年十月十日晚七时
7:00 P.M., October 10th, 1934
暑假实习  工厂操作机械留影
Summer Internship, Factory Photo
民国二十四年八月初三早八时
8:00 A.M., August 3rd, 1935
校园草坪野餐留影
Picnic in School Yard
民国二十三年五月初五上午十二时
12:00 P.M., May 5th, 1934
北平周一桐住地
Zhou Yitong's Peking Home
民国二十四年八月十七日下午三时
3:00 P.M., August 17th, 1935
北海公园郊游留影
Trip to Beihai Park
民国二十三年八月二十三日下午二时
2:00 P.M., August 23rd, 1934
燕京大学贝公楼礼堂学生音乐会演出留影
Student Concert at Bashford Hall, Yenching University
民国二十二年三月十八日晚八时
8:00 P.M., March 18th, 1933
燕京大学适楼小礼堂学生音乐会演出留影
Student Concert at Women's Dormitory, Yenching University
民国二十二年十月初五下午四时
4:00 P.M., October 5th, 1933
北平街道学生演讲抗议东北沦陷
Lecture at Student Protest of Japanese Occupation of Eastern China, Peking
民国二十二年六月十五日下午四时
4:00 P.M., June 15th, 1933
北平街道学生游行抗议日军暴行
Student Protest of Japanese Military Brutality
民国二十三年六月十七日上午十时
10:00 A.M. June 17th, 1934
燕京大学校园送行留影
Student Sendoff, Yenching University Campus
民国二十五年十月初五早八时
8:00 A.M., October 5th, 1936
燕京大学同学毕业留影
Graduation, Yenching University
民国二十五年六月二十八日下午五时
5:00 P.M., June 28th, 1936
燕京大学全体毕业生留影
Class Graduation Photo, Yenching University
民国二十五年七月初一上午十时
10:00 A.M., July 1st, 1936
敬予我们儿时的电影
To the movies we loved
我这个人吧  本身呢就
when we were young...
喜欢过去的事
I'm very much someone who likes things
过去的人
and people in the past.
他们说我就是一个特别怀旧
They all say I'm very nostalgic.
特别怀念过去的一个人
I'm someone who really misses the past.
很大的程度是因为
A big part of that is because
从小喜欢看老电影
I loved watching old movies when I was young.
我觉得我们现在的人呢
I feel like we in the modern era
离那个年代太遥远了
are very different than that era.
缺失了一些
I think we've lost some of their traditions.
传统的色彩
People in that era
在那个年代的人
had their own youths.
他们有他们的青春
They gave their entire
用生命完成自己的理想
life  over to an ideal.
我觉得这个是完美的时尚
I can't think of anything more perfect.
那个时候的人呢
People in those days
有一种浓重的中国烙印的
had a kind of deep Chinese flavor.
那种劲
A sort of strength.
对我来说我可能自己没有办法去
To me, I don't think I could ever
完成  没有办法去实现
finish that, I could never do that.
但是现在的人
But people today
要求的越来越多
demand more and more,
生活的越来越复杂
and live more complex lives,
权衡的也越来越多
they have to balance more than ever.
因此呢就
Which is why...
觉得现在的人呢好像差口气
I think, people today lack a sort of strength.
缺点勇气
They don't have bravery.
缺点魄力
They don't have courage.
缺点信仰
They don't have faith.
我如果真的有机会回去的话
If I really had the chance to go back,
可能自己没有办法去
I don't think I'd be able
完成  没有办法去实现
to finish that, to really do that.
如果设想这个电影里边
If I take this movie
所有的情节
and the plot,
如果我真的是他的话
and I imagine myself as my character,
再过几年回想来说
I would think back a few years later and think, wow,
挺精彩的
that was an awesome ride.